<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>In No Particular Order (meta)</title><link>https://isoboroff.github.io/</link><description>search, evaluation, social media, big data, and music</description><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 May 2013 15:06:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>nikola</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Home sweet home</title><link>https://isoboroff.github.io//posts/home-sweet-home.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Since Posterous is going away real soon now, I needed to migrate my
old site from pseudo.posterous.com.  Well, 'need' is of course a
relative term, but the old site did have some posts on using ClueWeb
and HBase which some folks might still find useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's nice that Posterous provided a way to bundle and download your
blog, but I decided to declare my independence (well, mostly) and move
the blog to a github pages site.  This way, the blog itself is
maintained in a git repository, and I can edit and push changes from
the command line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading &lt;a href="http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2013/05/07/migrating-from-octopress-to-pelican/"&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;
I spent some time reading up on static page generators and, after
playing with Jekyll-bootstrap and recoiling from its Ruby-ness (sorry, it's
just me), I settled on [Nikola][http://nikola.ralsina.com.ar/], which
is implemented in Python, a language I already speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Posterous dump comes down basically in WordPress format, and Nikola
can import that.  The
&lt;a href="http://nikola.ralsina.com.ar/handbook.html#importing-your-wordpress-site-into-nikola"&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt;
on that couldn't be simpler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To work with github, I followed some advice from &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/nikola-discuss/aDbsPtu4pNc"&gt;this
thread&lt;/a&gt;.
I created a branch called 'src', and in that branch set up a
virtualenv with Nikola and all the parts it wanted.  I then ported my
site, which created a directory 'new_site'.  'nikola build' went fine
after chasing down yet more Python packages for dates and Markdown.  I
then made a new clone of the git repository, copied the contents
of the 'output' directory, and committed that to the master branch.
Voila, everything in git and github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is really just a test post to see that everything's working.  If
it is, you can &lt;a href="https://github.com/isoboroff/isoboroff.github.com/blob/src/new_site/conf.py"&gt;see my
conf.py&lt;/a&gt;
which shows how its done.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>meta</category><guid>https://isoboroff.github.io//posts/home-sweet-home.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2013 18:36:19 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>